<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <standOff>
      <listPerson>
         <person/>
      </listPerson>
      <listPlace>
         <place/>
      </listPlace>
      <listEvent type="epoch">
         <event from="-0900" to="-0700" xml:id="Geometric">
            <eventName>Geometric Art</eventName>
            <idno>http://d-nb.info/gnd/4156729-8</idno>
         </event>
         <event from="-0700" to="-0490" xml:id="Archaic">
            <eventName>Archaic</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="-0490" to="-0330" xml:id="Classic">
            <eventName>Classic</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="-0330" to="-0030" xml:id="Hellenic">
            <eventName>Hellenic</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="-0753" to="-0509" xml:id="RomanMonarchy">
            <eventName>Hellenic</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="-0509" to="-0030" xml:id="RomanRepublic">
            <eventName>Roman Republic</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="-0030" to="0250" xml:id="RomanEmpire">
            <eventName>Roman</eventName>
         </event>
         <event from="0250" to="0500" xml:id="LateAntiquity">
            <eventName>Late Antiquity</eventName>
         </event>
      </listEvent>
      <listEvent type="historical">
         <event>
            <eventName></eventName>
         </event>
      </listEvent>
      <listEvent type="mythological">
         <event>
            <eventName></eventName>
         </event>
      </listEvent>
      <listRelation>
         <relation name="parent" active="#Aigeus" passive="#Theseus"/>
      </listRelation>
   </standOff>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="book" n="1">
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <div type="section" n="1">
                  <p xml:id="p1_1_1"> On the Greek mainland facing the Cyclades Islands and the Aegean Sea the
                     Sunium promontory stands out from the Attic land. When you have rounded the
                     promontory you see a harbor and a temple to Athena of Sunium on the peak of the
                     promontory. Farther on is Laurium, where once the Athenians had silver mines,
                     and a small uninhabited island called the Island of Patroclus. For a
                     fortification was built on it and a palisade constructed by Patroclus, who was
                     admiral in command of the Egyptian men-of-war sent by Ptolemy, son of Ptolemy,
                     son of Lagus, to help the Athenians, when Antigonus, son of Demetrius, was
                     ravaging their country, which he had invaded with an army, and at the same time
                     was blockading them by sea with a fleet </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="2">
                  <p xml:id="p1_1_2">The Peiraeus was a parish from early times, though it was not a port before
                     Themistocles became an archon of the Athenians.1 Their port was Phalerum, for
                     at this place the sea comes nearest to Athens, and from here men say that
                     Menestheus set sail with his fleet for Troy, and before him Theseus, when he
                     went to give satisfaction to Minos for the death of Androgeos. But when
                     Themistocles became archon, since he thought that the Peiraeus was more
                     conveniently situated for mariners, and had three harbors as against one at
                     Phalerum, he made it the Athenian port. Even up to my time there were docks
                     there, and near the largest harbor is the grave of Themistocles. For it is said
                     that the Athenians repented of their treatment of Themistocles, and that his
                     relations took up his bones and brought them from Magnesia. And the children of
                     Themistocles certainly returned and set up in the Parthenon a painting, on
                     which is a portrait of Themistocles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="3">
                  <p xml:id="p1_1_3">The most noteworthy sight in the Peiraeus is a precinct of Athena and Zeus.
                     Both their images are of bronze; Zeus holds a staff and a Victory, Athena a
                     spear. Here is a portrait of Leosthenes and of his sons, painted by Arcesilaus.
                     This Leosthenes at the head of the Athenians and the united Greeks defeated the
                     Macedonians in Boeotia and again outside Thermopylae forced them into Lamia
                     over against Oeta, and shut them up there.1 The portrait is in the long
                     portico, where stands a market-place for those living near the sea—those
                     farther away from the harbor have another—but behind the portico near the sea
                     stand a Zeus and a Demos, the work of Leochares. And by the sea Conon2 built a
                     sanctuary of Aphrodite, after he had crushed the Lacedaemonian warships off
                     Cnidus in the Carian peninsula.3 For the Cnidians hold Aphrodite in very great
                     honor, and they have sanctuaries of the goddess; the oldest is to her as
                     Doritis （Bountiful）, the next in age as Acraea （Of the Height）, while the
                     newest is to the Aphrodite called Cnidian by men generally, but Euploia （Fair
                     Voyage） by the Cnidians themselves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="4">
                  <p xml:id="p1_1_4">The Athenians have also another harbor, at Munychia, with a temple of Artemis
                     of Munychia, and yet another at Phalerum, as I have already stated, and near it
                     is a sanctuary of Demeter. Here there is also a temple of Athena Sciras, and
                     one of Zeus some distance away, and altars of the gods named Unknown, and of
                     heroes, and of the children of Theseus and Phalerus; for this Phalerus is said
                     by the Athenians to have sailed with Jason to Colchis. There is also an altar
                     of Androgeos, son of Minos, though it is called that of Heros; those, however,
                     who pay special attention to the study of their country's antiquities know that
                     it belongs to Androgeos.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section" n="5">
                  <p xml:id="p1_1_5">Twenty stades away is the Coliad promontory; on to it, when the Persian fleet
                     was destroyed, the wrecks were carried down by the waves. There is here an
                     image of the Coliad Aphrodite, with the goddesses Genetyllides （Goddesses of
                     Birth）, as they are called. And I am of opinion that the goddesses of the
                     Phocaeans in Ionia, whom they call Gennaides, are the same as those at Colias.
                     On the way from Phalerum to Athens there is a temple of Hera with neither doors
                     nor roof. Men say that Mardonius, son of Gobryas, burnt it. But the image there
                     to-day is, as report goes, the work of Alcamenes1 So that this, at any rate,
                     cannot have been damaged by the Persians.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
